<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="snowcap_decoration_v1">
    <copyright>
        Copyright © 2025 Ottatop

        Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person
        obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation
        files (the “Software”), to deal in the Software without
        restriction, including without limitation the rights to use, copy,
        modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies
        of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
        furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

        The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be
        included in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

        THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED “AS IS”, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND,
        EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF
        MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND
        NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS
        BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN
        ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF OR IN
        CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE
        SOFTWARE.
    </copyright>

    <description summary="let clients draw server-side decorations">
        This protocol enables clients to draw decorations that are used by the compositor
        to decorate toplevels.
    </description>

    <interface name="snowcap_decoration_manager_v1" version="1">
        <description summary="create surfaces that can decorate toplevels">
            Clients can use this interface to assign the snowcap_decoration_surface_v1 role
            to wl_surfaces. Such surfaces are rendered attached to toplevels. Xwayland
            windows are considered toplevels for this protocol.
        </description>

        <request name="get_decoration_surface">
            <description summary="create a decoration surface from a wl_surface">
                Creates a decoration surface for an existing surface. This assigns the role of
                snowcap_decoration_surface_v1, or raises a protocol error if another role is
                already assigned.

                Creating a decoration surface from a wl_surface which has a buffer attached
                or committed is a client error, and any attempts by a client to attach
                or manipulate a buffer prior to the first decoration_surface.configure call
                must also be treated as errors.

                After creating a decoration_surface object and setting it up, the client must
                perform an initial commit without any buffer attached. The compositor
                will reply with a decoration_surface.configure event. The client must
                acknowledge it and is then allowed to attach a buffer to map the surface.
            </description>
            <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="snowcap_decoration_surface_v1"/>
            <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
            <arg name="toplevel" type="object" interface="ext_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1"/>
        </request>

        <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
            <description summary="destroy the decoration manager object">
                This request indicates that the client will not use the decoration manager object
                anymore. Objects that have been created through this instance are not affected.
            </description>
        </request>

        <enum name="error">
            <entry name="role" value="0" summary="wl_surface has another role"/>
            <entry name="already_constructed" value="1" summary="wl_surface has a buffer attached or committed"/>
        </enum>
    </interface>

    <interface name="snowcap_decoration_surface_v1" version="1">
        <description summary="decoration interface">
            An interface that may be implemented by a wl_surface
            for surfaces that are designed to decorate toplevels.

            Attaching a null buffer to a decoration surface does *not*
            unmap it, unlike other shell protocols.
        </description>

        <request name="set_location">
            <description summary="set the location of the decoration surface">
                The location of a decoration surface is its position
                relative to the top-left corner of the decorated toplevel
                (as set by xdg_toplevel.set_window_geometry and taking into
                account set bounds).

                If the toplevel has multiple decorations with differing bounds
                set, each decoration surface is rendered relative to its own
                set bounds.

                Geometry is double-buffered; see wl_surface.commit.
            </description>
            <arg name="x" type="int" summary="x-coordinate relative to the top-left corner including bounds" />
            <arg name="y" type="int" summary="y-coordinate relative to the top-left corner including bounds" />
        </request>

        <request name="set_bounds">
            <description summary="set the bounds of the toplevel the decoration surface is decorating">
                Extends the bounds of the toplevel this surface is decorating.

                This request can be used to extend the toplevel's effective
                geometry to encompass parts or all of the decoration
                surface. For example, a titlebar surface with
                a height of 16 logical pixels may issue this request
                with top equal to 16 to include it in the toplevel's
                geometry.

                The compositor should treat the toplevel as having a size
                extended by the given amounts in each direction, even if the
                decoration surface has no buffer attached.
                If multiple clients have set bounds, the bounds of the toplevel
                are the maximum set for each edge.

                On commit, the compositor must respond to this request with a configure event
                with the new inner size of the toplevel.

                Bounds are double-buffered; see wl_surface.commit.
            </description>
            <arg name="left" type="uint" summary="amount to extend the left edge leftward" />
            <arg name="right" type="uint" summary="amount to extend the right edge rightward" />
            <arg name="top" type="uint" summary="amount to extend the top edge upward" />
            <arg name="bottom" type="uint" summary="amount to extend the bottom edge downward" />
        </request>

        <request name="set_z_index">
            <description summary="set the z-index the decoration surface">
                Sets the z-index at which the decoration surface will
                render and receive pointer input.

                Negative indices place the surface below the decorated toplevel.
                All other indices place it above.

                Decoration surfaces with a higher set index render above
                those with a lower one.

                Decoration surfaces with the same index are rendered
                in a compositor-defined manner.

                If unset, the index is 0.

                Z-index is double-buffered; see wl_surface.commit.
            </description>
            <arg name="z_index" type="int" summary="index to render the surface at" />
        </request>

        <request name="get_popup">
            <description summary="assign this decoration surface as an xdg_popup parent">
                This assigns an xdg_popup's parent to this decoration surface.
                This popup should have been created via xdg_surface::get_popup
                with the parent set to NULL, and this request must be invoked before
                committing the popup's initial state.

                See the documentation of xdg_popup for more details about what
                an xdg_popup is and how it is used.
            </description>
            <arg name="popup" type="object" interface="xdg_popup"/>
        </request>

        <request name="ack_configure">
            <description summary="acknowledge a configure request">
                When a configure event is received, if a client commits the
                surface in response to the configure event, then the client
                must make an ack_configure request sometime before the commit
                request, passing along the serial of the configure event.

                If the client receives multiple configure events before it
                can respond to one, it only has to ack the last configure event.

                A client is not required to commit immediately after sending
                an ack_configure request - it may even ack_configure several times
                before its next surface commit.

                A client may send multiple ack_configure requests before committing, but
                only the last request sent before a commit indicates which configure
                event the client really is responding to.
            </description>
            <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="the serial from the configure event" />
        </request>

        <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
            <description summary="destroy the decoration surface object">
                This request destroys the decoration surface.
            </description>
        </request>

        <event name="configure">
            <description summary="suggest a surface change">
                The configure event asks the client to resize its decoration surface.

                Clients should arrange their surface for the new states, and then send
                an ack_configure request with the serial sent in this configure event at
                some point before committing the new surface.

                The client is free to dismiss all but the last configure event it
                received.

                The width and height arguments specify the inner size of the
                *toplevel being decorated* in surface-local coordinates,
                ignoring set bounds.
                The client should update its decoration surface for a toplevel
                of the received size.

                The compositor must not send a configure event where either the
                width, height, or both are 0.
            </description>
            <arg name="serial" type="uint" />
            <arg name="width" type="uint" summary="the width of the toplevel being decorated, ignoring bounds" />
            <arg name="height" type="uint" summary="the height of the toplevel being decorated, ignoring bounds" />
        </event>

        <event name="closed">
            <description summary="surface should be closed">
                The closed event is sent by the compositor when the surface will
                no longer be shown. The output may have been destroyed or the
                user may have asked for it to be removed. Further changes to the
                surface will be ignored. The client should destroy the resource
                after receiving this event, and create a new surface if they so choose.
            </description>
        </event>
    </interface>
</protocol>
